Preliminary Guide to the John Emory Bryant Papers, 1851-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Emory Bryant papers 1851-1955 and undated
Bryant, John Emory
3.14 linear feet Extent: 2,358 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00167
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Emory Bryant Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1968 and 2002.
Biographical Note
Abolitionist, Union officer with the 8th Maine Volunteers, agent of the Freedmen's Bureau, and Republican politician; from Union, Me.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, published writings and other papers, and scrapbooks (accession #68-34) (1,858 items; dated 1851-1907), relating to Bryant's Civil War service in South Carolina with the 8th Maine Volunteers, his activities as agent with the Freedmen's Bureau in Georgia, as a leader of the Negro Republicans in Georgia (1865-1887), his business ventures, and his interests in temperance and the Methodist Church. Correspondents include William Anderson Pledger and Henry McNeal Turner.
Addition (accession #2002-0175) (500 items, 2 lin. ft.; dated 1853-1955 and undated) contains correspondence; 5 black-and-white photographs and 10 albumen prints; and documents relating to Bryant, his family, and his involvement with the Freedmen's Bureau, the Republican Party, and African-American affairs in Georgia. Most of the letters are originals; many of the other items are copies or typescripts.
Subject Headings
Bryant, John Emory, 1836-1900; Pledger, William Anderson; Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915; Bryant family; Republican Party (Ga.); Methodist Episcopal Church -- Georgia; United States. Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands; United States. Army. Maine Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1866); African Americans -- Georgia; Reconstruction -- Georgia; Freedmen -- Georgia; African American Republicans -- Georgia; Temperance -- United States; South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Georgia -- History -- 1865-; Scrapbooks; Black-and-white photographs; Albumen prints
Contents of Collection
- Accession 68-34
  - Letters, 1851-1863 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1864-1869 (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1870-1875 (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1876-1879 (Box 4)
  - Letters, 1880-1907 (Box 5)
  - Legal Papers (Box 6)
  - Financial Papers (Box 6)
  - Official Papers and Writings: Misc. (Box 6)
  - Official Papers and Writings: Methodist, 1878-1887 (Box 6)
  - Official Papers and Writings: Political, 1866-1892 (Box 7)
  - Journal of J.E. Bryant, 1853-1859 (Box 7)
  - Journal of Emma Bryant, 1866, 1876 (Box 7)
  - Autobiography of Alice Zeller (Box 7)
  - Letter Books of J.E. Bryant (Box 8)
    - 1876-1877 (Box 8)
    - 1888-1891 (Box 8)
  - William Anderson Pledger (Box 9)
  - Letterpress Book, 1875-1879 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1874-1889 (Box 9)
  - Volumes: C.S.A. Army Records (Box 10)
  - Volumes: Scrapbooks, 1861-1875 (Box 11)
    Including Scrapbook, 1861-1866, with Civil War orders and Freemen's Bureau materials
  - Volumes: Scrapbooks, New York City and Athens, Tennessee, 1887-1890s (Box 12)
  - Volumes: Account Books (Box 13)
  - Volumes: Account Books (Box 14)
  - Printed Materials: Clippings (Box 15)
  - Printed Materials: Pamphlets, Broadsides and Leaflets (Xerox and Originals) (Box 16)
- Accession 2002-0175
  - Correspondence, 1854-1916 (Box 1)
  - Sons of Temperance, State of Maine documents, 1860-1861 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents, 1866-1874 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers, letters and excerpts from books, by and about J.E. Bryant, 1853-1882 and undated (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Civics, 1886 and undated (Box 1)
  - Documents concerning Bryant's death, 1900-1909 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes a copy of Bryant's death certificate.
  - Church related documents, 1886-1889 (Box 1)
  - Deposit Book of the National Freedman's Savings and Trust Co., 1868 (Box 2)
  - Documents related to the Civil War, 1864-1905 (Box 2)
  - Day to Day Life and Thoughts of John Emory Bryant, written by Raymond Bryant Zeller, [1950s] (Box 2)
    This biography was written by Raymond B. Zeller about 1955 from Bryant's journals and other papers. It was never published.
  - Genealogical information and Biography, undated (Box 2)
    The genealogy was complied by Margaret Zeller Garrett. The biography was written by Fred O. Smith for a school paper and was in turn sent to Raymond Bryant Zeller by Smith, Zeller's nephew.
  - Printed Material, 1914-1915 and undated (Box 2)
    Included here is a letter to, and telegram from, President Ulysses S. Grant pertaining to the appointment of a custom collector.
  - Journals
    - J.E. Bryant Journal #5 (RBZ's typed copy), [1950s] (Box 2)
    - J.E. Bryant Journal #3 (RBZ's typed copy), [1950s] (Box 2)
    - Bryant's 1900 Diary (copy) (Box 2)
    - Diary For the Year 1900 (Box 2)
      Written by both Bryant and his wife Emma.
  - Notes by Emma Spaulding Bryant 25 Dec. 1900 - 31 Dec. 1900 (Box 2)
  - Emma's Sketch Book, undated (Box 2)
  - 5 black and white photographs, undated (Box 2)
    Photographs include John Emory Bryant, his wife Emma and their only child Emma Alice Bryant Zeller, and Alice's first child Miriam.
  - Photograph book of senior Union Officers, undated (Box 2)
    A list of names of these officers is written in the back numbered 1-40.
  - Misc., 1883-1897 and undated (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1866-1895 (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1895-1898 (Box 4)
  - Letters, 1898-1900 and undated (Box 5)
  - Recipes for Medicine, 1872 and undated (Box 5)
  - Calling Cards, undated (Box 5)